<essaylist>
	<essay>
		<title>The Shattering Force of War</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2009-10</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;British poet and World War I soldier Wilfred Owen demonstrates the gruesome and stygian nature of war in his poem “Dulce et Decorum Est”. Owen begins his work with descriptions of war life, the everyday experience the soldiers endure in the trenches. He describes the utter misery the soldiers bear. This misery in the trenches is juxtaposed to the torturous death of one of the speaker’s fellow soldiers by gas, as he thrashes like “man in fire or lime” and lies dying, to show that soldiers must live deprived periods of time in the trenches just to watch each other die, one at a time. There is no glory in fighting, just horrific, pointless death. Owen employs macabre imagery and metaphors, as he describes the soldier drowning in a green sea of gas, his “white eyes writhing in his face”. He uses this to show to the reader the grotesque deaths soldiers must die, as opposed to the glorious notions presented by propaganda and other poems like “The Charge of the Light Brigade”. Owen further refutes this notion of glorious death in war when he calls the saying “Dulce et decorum est pro patria mori”, which translates to, “It is glorious and honorable to die for one’s country” an old lie. The refutation of this saying and the torturous death of the soldier both show that rather than being glorious and honorable, a death in war is a terrible and painful experience for both the victim and onlookers. War, to Owen, is more repulsive than it is glorious.lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Wilfred Owen and Erich Maria Remarque, both World War I soldiers, think the notion of glorious death in war absurd. Like Owen, Remarque shows the mentally oppressive and emotional straining conditions of war in the trenches in his book, All Quiet on the Western Front, as well as the death and imagery in the death of a comrade. For example, Paul, the protagonist from Remarque’s work, witnesses the tension in his comrades and the new recruits in anticipation of a bombardment, and later, the dismemberment of a new recruit who had escaped the trench out of fear. As the recruit is blown apart, Paul sees that “the wall of the trench is plastered with smoking splinters, lumps of flesh, and bits of uniform” (111). Like the speaker in Owen’s poem, Paul sees his fellow soldiers dying these revolting deaths every day, and eventually has become numb; death, for World War I soldiers like Paul and Owen’s speaker, has become everyday and meaningless. As young soldiers like these boys become numb to death, they no longer see it as glorious, but rather, take a practical approach to it. “Dulce et Decorum Est” and All Quiet on the Western Front both show that the images of a glorious death in war that has been ingrained into the minds of the people of the times of World War I are simply illusions covering up a sickening truth, the horrors of war.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Having never been in a war or seen death in war, I relate to this poem through its imagery. Owen writes this poem using metaphors comparing the experiences of war to everyday experiences and events, like when he describes the deadly gas bomb as a “green sea”. Also, as an analytically inclined person, this poem speaks to my philosophical self. Although the modern media tries to implant ideas of how fighting for one’s country is glorious, this poem’s analysis of the horrors of war reveal the dark side of military conflict. Although I see commercials about the glorious, adventurous nature of joining the armed forces, Owen’s work explains the other side of the issue: the death and depravity of war. I can relate to this poem in that although it was written in an earlier time that has become blurry to most people or my generation, it is also applicable to the modern, universal issues of militarism and war.
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>Compare and Contrast: Hero's Journey</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2009-10</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Can identity be found through one’s sojourn through life? Is identity purely based on experience, or can it be found from within? Every person is on his or her own journey through life. Throughout life, each individual crosses a threshold into the journey of experience, and encounters tests, challenges, and enemies. People combat foes such as those of the trickster, shapeshifter, and shadow archetypes. All individuals fight alongside allies, mentors, and friends. Everyone faces an ultimately defining ordeal in life, and brings back a reward, be it tangible or not. Such is the Monomyth theory of famous mythologist Joseph Campbell, in which everyone, real or fictional, is on his or her own “hero’s journey”. It is this journey and how it is lived that ultimately defines individuals in life. Albert Einstein and Bellerophon are salient examples of this fact. Einstein’s quest is metaphorical; his search for scientific knowledge, driven by his curiosity, is a hero’s journey. Einstein’s motivation for undertaking such a quest was curiosity and a desire to help advance the human race in scientific development. Belleraphon’s journey, on the other hand, is a journey for redemption for accidentally killing his brother. However, although they differed in motivation, Einstein and Bellerophon both found identity through their “hero’s journeys”. From their humble beginnings to their rise to glory, and to their ultimate downfall, Einstein and Bellerophon exemplify that identity is defined through one’s experiences. Therefore, although Einstein and Bellerophon lived in different societies, and Einstein was motivated to write the future while Bellerophon was motivated to erase the past, both found identity in their journeys through life.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Einstein and Bellerophon’s humble beginnings and rise to glory show that identity comes from experience. For example, although the beginnings of Einstein and Bellerophon’s journeys posed great challenges and tests, both persevered and overcame their circumstances, defining their identities. Einstein began his journey as a virtual nonentity. He acted far too rebelliously in school to be respected by his teachers or peers. Einstein’s family was not rich, nor did it include many prominent scientists. Einstein did not have his outstanding intelligence as a child, either. According to biographer Walter Isaacson in Einstein: His Life and Universe, as a young boy, Einstein had a “slow development… combined with a cheeky rebelliousness toward authority” (Issacson 8). Einstein’s overcoming of these obstacles to become a scientist considered foremost in the world gave him an identity. His triumph over these tests defined him as persistent and slightly dogmatic. Bellerophon has worse beginnings. Having killed his brother, Bellerophon begins his journey as a murderer, but performs numerous tasks to gain redemption. On his journey to redeem himself, Bellerophon is tempted by King Proetus’s wife, and is framed for defiling her. However, despite the problems that harry this hero at the beginning of his journey, he presses on, and accomplishes the tasks that would win him his redemption. Bellerophon’s perseverance in overcoming these problems ultimately defines him. On his quest, Bellerophon shows that he is unwilling to live with his wrongs, and needs to redeem himself in order to move on. Bellerophon’s perseverance shows that he is a man of high moral standards. The fact that Einstein and Bellerophon both found identity in their rise to glory shows that identity comes only from the process, the journey it takes to overcome the numerous tests in life. Identity emerges from experience.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Both Einstein and Bellerophon defined themselves on their journeys through overcoming a seemingly impossible ordeal. For example, Bellerophon’s ordeal is the Chimera, a fire-breathing monster with a lion, snake, and goat head that had killed every single hero who had fought it. However, even this mighty beast could not defeat Bellerophon, who rides the winged horse Pegasus and uses a spear with a head of lead to slay the Chimera. This ordeal defines Bellerophon both internally and externally; both his self-identity and social identity are affected. Bellerophon defines himself as fearless and creative, and wins himself much fame in the eyes of society. The ancient Greeks valued fame and glory, so Bellerophon has identity in the eyes of others. He also created his own self-identity. Einstein’s ordeal defined him as well. His ordeal was a quest for an explanation of gravity. Gravity had been discovered and mathematically quantified by Sir Isaac Newton. However, Newton left the actual mechanism by which gravity worked unexplained, as a mysterious attraction between all objects. Einstein “probed the equivalence of inertial mass and gravitational mass” (Issacson 147), and slew this metaphorical “beast” that is the gravity puzzle through formulating the Theory of Relativity. In doing so, Einstein found his identity as a scientist; his momentous achievement that has forever altered modern physics defined him as both creative and innovative. Both Einstein and Bellerophon defined themselves through their greatest ordeals, which shows that experience is the source of identity.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Throughout their journeys, Einstein and Bellerophon showed a flaw that ultimately defined them. For example, Einstein’s downfall as a scientist resulted directly from his Hubris, that is, pride. Near the end of his life, Einstein tried to find an equation, a “Theory of Everything” that would explain everything in the universe. He coined a phrase summing up the main ideas within his theory, that nothing is random: “I am convinced that He [God] does not play dice” (Einstein). In this arrogant assertion, Einstein declares that he has the potential to find an all-encompassing theory, demonstrating his Hubris. Due to his Hubris, Einstein overestimated his abilities, and ultimately became known to the scientific community as an outdated, crazy professor. Because of Hubris, Einstein fell from his glorious fame as the world’s foremost scientist. This shows that identity is defined not only by an individual’s successes in the hero’s journey, but also in the individual’s failures. Identity is found throughout all elements of the journey through life. In addition, Bellerophon exhibits his own Hubris when he tries to fly to mount Olympus. After he accomplished so many tasks, Bellerophon thought of himself as god, and his pride got the best of him. As Bellerophon nears the gates of Olympus, Zeus strikes him down, sending Bellerophon hurtling back to earth, crippling and blinding him. Because he tried to ascend to the status of the gods, Bellerophon lives the rest of his life as a rejected wanderer. This hero’s downfall shows that all traits, even flaws, can define one’s identity in the journey of life. Hubris demonstrates Einstein and Bellerophon’s human pride and limitations as people, despite their heroic status.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The fact that Einstein and Bellerophon followed a strict moral throughout their journeys code defined their identities. For example, although Einstein lived in an age of war and could have easily gained glory by joining the ranks of military scientists, he was strictly against all forms of warfare. Although one can argue that Einstein’s letter to President Roosevelt regarding the atomic bomb is consider an act of military science, the letter was a warning, and Einstein had no intention of allowing his discovery to be used to take lives. When speaking on his opinions about peace and war, Einstein said, “How despicable and ignoble war is; I would rather be torn to shreds than be a part of so base an action. It is my conviction that killing under the cloak of war is nothing but an act of murder” (Einstein). Einstein clearly hates all forms of warfare, and has fought against the temptation to use his discoveries for military purposes all throughout his life. By following his principles, Einstein defined himself as a man of morals and someone who sticks to his ideals. This shows that individuals need to follow a principle or value throughout their hero’s journey to find identity. By following a code of honor all throughout their hero’s journeys, individuals can find identity. In addition, Bellerophon follows a code of purity, and refuses the advances of the queen of Tiryns. Although the queen was a woman of great influence and power, Bellerophon still refuses, in order to respect his host, the king. By sticking to his values, Bellerophon finds identity in his morals. This shows that all individuals, no matter how separate by time, culture, or distance, can still find identity in their morals and values. Clearly, Einstein and Belleraphon’s values have defined them throughout their journeys. These strict adherences to a moral code show that Einstein and Bellerophon find identity in their honor. They have defined themselves as men of principles.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Einstein and Bellerophon had different motives for their journeys, but both still found identity. For example, although Einstein’s motivation in his journey was discovery and curiosity, and not to find identity, he, nevertheless, still found identity through his journey through science for the ultimate goal of discovery. Einstein embarked on his scientific quest to discover for the future of humanity, driven by his curiosity. In fact, he once said, “The important thing is not to stop questioning. Curiosity has its own reason for existing” (Einstein). However, at the end of his quest, Einstein found something more valuable, identity, even though it was not his initial purpose. This shows that Einstein’s search for identity is not truly a search, but an unconscious result of his journey through life. Identity is not a conscious achievement; rather, it comes from experience in the journey through life. In contrast, unlike Einstein, Bellerophon is motivated by a desire to erase the past through redemption. However, at the end of his journey, Bellerophon still is able to define himself. Bellerophon wants to redeem himself for killing his brother through his quest, but ends up finding identity. This shows that Bellerophon’s search for redemption defines him, whether he intends it or not. The search, journey, or quest that one partakes transcends motives, and ultimately defines one’s identity.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Although Einstein and Bellerophon lived in different ages, and their societies had some bearing on their unique expressions of the hero’s journey, they still found identity on their quests. For example, Einstein lived in a contemporary age of science and technology. Society valued individual achievement and pursuit. However, Einstein still found identity through his quest in science. This shows that Einstein’s quest led to ultimate self-definition, even though he lives in a different age. Individuals can find identity through experience, no matter the society in which they live. In addition, although Bellerophon lives in ancient Greek society, a Homeric “shame culture”, in which individuals are less responsible for personal morals than for public standing, fame, and glory, he ultimately finds identity. Although the society in which Bellerophon lives had some bearing on his quest for redemption, such as why he needed redemption in the first place, Bellerophon eventually defines himself on his journey. This shows that Bellerophon’s self-definition comes not from his surrounding world, but his individual journey. Individuals’ success in the search for identity on their journeys throughout life is not affected by society, but rather by the journey itself.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Identity is found through one’s experiences in life. Although Einstein and Bellerophon’s motivations for embarking on their heroic journeys differ, and their journeys took place in different times and cultures, both found identity on their quests. This goes to show that in all individuals living in all societies, identity is achieved through the journey that is life. Experience, the only source of identity, transcends cultural and personality barriers. Experience defines individuals.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Works Cited&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"Homeric Society, Univ. of Saskatchewan." Homepage. Web. 15 Dec. 2009. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Isaacson, Walter. Einstein His Life and Universe. New York: Simon and Schuster, 2007. Print.
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>21st Century Scarlet Letter</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2010-11</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;All humans are imperfect and possess traits that merit public ignominy and shunning. Why, then is society, a creation of mankind and an institution composed of imperfect humans, so ready to shun public figures, when all humans possess these faults? George W. Bush, the 43rd president of the United States of America, is one such public figure whose reputation has declined gravely due to the readiness of mankind to direct their angst and insecurities against other people with faults. President Bush possessed one main fault that destroyed his reputation and made him a figure of both public scorn and opposition from his own political party: starting the costly Iraq War. However, society overlooks Bush’s merits, such as his education and societal reforms. This social branding is similar to that of Hester Prynne from The Scarlet Letter, who suffered public humiliation because of her sin of adultery. Society overlooks Hester’s benevolent deeds and focuses mainly on her faults. However, if all humans possess faults that merit ignominy, and they emphasize the misdeeds of others and overlook their munificence, then they do so to ease their self-doubt from their own faults. Thus, individuals in society shun others by overlooking good deeds and accentuating sins to alleviate their feelings about their own faults.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Society shuns President George W. Bush mainly because he started a costly war in Iraq under the excuse of national security. The Iraq War originally began as the Afghanistan War, a widely supported war on terrorism that started after the September 11th attacks. However, the widely supported war in Afghanistan became a poorly supported war in Iraq when Bush decided that “Saddam Hussein and his supporters were an imminent threat to our safety [because of their alleged possession of weapons of mass destruction], and the Bush Administration argued that the best way to combat terrorism, in general, was to go on offense” (Burnett). However, in the end, “No weapons of mass destruction have ever been located” (Burnett). Meanwhile, the war had cost taxpayers $5000 for every second since the beginning of the war in March 20, 2003 (“Iraq War Statistics”), and led to approximately 42,899 American casualties (“Casualties in Iraq”) and at least 98,380 Iraqi casualties (Iraq Body Count). George W. Bush, by bringing the nation into a wild goose chase for alleged weapons of mass destruction in a costly, unpopular war, compromised the trust of the people. In turn, the American people directed their anger and shunning towards the individual who made this mistake, Bush himself. The populace branded Bush with scarlet letter “B” for “belligerent”. This demonstrates a tendency of society and humans in general towards a focus on the faults of public figures. Shunning, in turn, is a result of this emphasis of individuals’ wrongs, in this case, the war in Iraq. By shunning President Bush for his actions in Iraq, common members of society make their own faults appear meager when compared to the towering flaws of Bush’s leadership.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;George W. Bush has suffered various losses due to society’s shunning, the most significant being his political standing. For instance, according to Washington Post political writer Richard Morin, “fewer than half of the respondents approve of the job Bush is doing, while majorities express dissatisfaction with him on Iraq (62 percent)”( Poll Finds Bush). During his second term, President Bush’s political ratings dropped greatly, possibly crippling his political career. Because of his mistake in Iraq, among other issues, Bush lost the trust of the American people. As a result of public shunning and ignominy, Bush’s political career and social standing took a great fall. This fall took place not only in the grand arena of American politics, but also within Bush’s own political party. In the 2008 presidential elections, Republican presidential candidate John McCain “supports the US war in Iraq, but was critical of Bush’s handling”(Issues - Iraq). From his management of the war in Iraq, Bush earned enmity from even the leading candidate in his own political party. To preserve its own political standing, the Republican Party and its representatives disown Bush. Bush lost not only the support of the general populace, but even the support of his own political party, to public shunning.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Both George W. Bush, a modern figure, and Hester Prynne, a figure from Puritan society, committed sins considered atrocious by the society in which they lived and had their achievements and acts of charity overlooked. For example, when Hester stands on the scaffold while holding her infant daughter, Pearl, in the beginning of The Scarlet Letter, “The unhappy culprit sustained herself… under the heavy weight of a thousand unrelenting eyes, all fastened upon her and concentrated at [the scarlet letter on] her bosom”(Hawthorne 64). The public decides to ignore the beautiful child in Hester’s hands, the true product of Hester’s sin, but rather, focus upon the superficial symbol of adultery, the letter branded upon Hester’s chest. Likewise, the general populace overlooks the fact that George W. Bush’s War on Iraq and the search for nonexistent weapons of mass destruction was an effort to defend the American people against a nuclear threat and an incident that would prove far worse than the September 11th attacks. The people choose to ignore the benevolent intentions behind Bush’s decision to start the war, but rather, shun him for the resulting costs of war, just as the Puritan populace in Hester’s day ignored Pearl and focused on the sin of adultery represented by the letter. By doing this, individuals who choose to shun others alleviate anxieties about their own sins and faults that merit shame. In addition, after her public ignominy on the scaffold, Hester lived life as a seamstress, and “bestowed all her superfluous means in charity, on wretches less miserable than herself, and who not unfrequently insulted the hand that fed them” (Hawthorne 87). Hester spent a considerable amount of her resources on charity. However, society clearly overlooks this, as the “wretches” who receive charity from Hester insult her as an adulteress; in other words, society overlooks Hester’s goodwill and focuses more on her sin. Similarly, society despises George W. Bush for his war on Iraq, among other wrongs. However, it overlooks his achievements and social reforms, especially in the area of education. President Bush enacted the No Child Left Behind act, supported foreign language programs, and enacted measures that would “Give options for kids trapped in failing schools” (George W. Bush). However, just as society chooses to overlook Hester’s charity, society also overlooks President Bush’s reforms in favor of his sins. Thus, by shunning public figures such as Hester and Bush, the populaces of both the puritan and modern worlds make their own sins seem miniscule.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Society overlooks munificence and emphasizes misdeeds of public figures in order to alleviate anxieties about personal sins and faults. Shunning is a direct result of human nature and its own flaws. The fall of George W. Bush from his political reputation and society’s failure to recognize his merits along with the sins it is so ready to emphasize are a testament to the nature of shame; shunning occurs because all individuals have faults that make them worthy of society’s hatred. In American culture, individuals are quick to judge public figures such as politicians like Bush, social pariahs like Hester, or celebrities. However, individuals must recognize that such angst against the faults of public figures is a direct result of their own sins; when shunning is viewed in this light, it is hypocrisy and should never happen.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Works Cited&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Burnett, By Bob. "One, Two, Three, What Are We Fighting For?" Common Dreams | News and Views. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"Casualties in Iraq." Antiwar.com. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"George W. Bush on the Issues." OnTheIssues.org - Candidates on the Issues. Web. 25 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Hawthorne, Nathaniel. The Scarlet Letter. New York: Bantam, 1986. Print.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Iraq Body Count. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"Iraq War Statistics." Iraq War. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"Issues - Iraq - Where Republican Candidates Stand - Campaign 2008." Boston.com. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;"Poll Finds Bush Job Rating at New Low - Washingtonpost.com." Washington Post - Politics, National, World and D.C. Area News and Headlines - Washingtonpost.com. Web. 22 Oct. 2010. 
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>The Cyborg Dawn</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2011-12</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;“We are the Borg. Existence, as you know it, is over. We will add your biological and technological distinctiveness to our own. Resistance is futile.” This is the universal greeting of the Borg Collective, a race from the philosophical science fiction series Star Trek, whose technology has become so advanced that it has become an integral part of their anatomy. In the show, the Borg are able to enhance their bodies far beyond their biological capacities using cybernetic implants, rendering them anatomically superior to their unmodified counterparts. The fictional Borg species raises an interesting question: will human technology advance to such a degree in the next fifty years that we would be able to enhance, improve, and transcend our flawed corporal existence? Current trends seem to side with the affirmative; 1999 Nobel Prize winner A. Zewail (2008) states that “the reduction of the physical size of computers and the increase in their computation capacity and speed” (p. 230) has precipitated an exponential trend of technological growth. This flurry of development in computer technology has, as stated by Zewail, helped bring about modern trends of advancement, including growth by leaps and bounds in areas like neurobiological computational technology and augmented reality, thereby enhancing human perception. The recent growth in humanity’s computational prowess has also allowed for an increase in the efficiency of engineering and scientific processes, allowing for the development of biotechnology that allows for repairs of the human anatomy, and mechanical contraptions to give it superhuman capabilities. All these trends indicate a point where we, as humans, can use technology to enhance our corporal existences. Thus, in fifty years, humanity will have the technology to transcend its anatomical limitations through mechanical, biological, and perceptual enhancements.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;In fifty years, humanity will have the ability to enhance the body’s mechanical design. This is a necessary development, as “the human figure is by no means optimal. When nature designed us, the quadruped animal was remodeled. Two front legs had to be used as arms, and the biped was the only selection” (Hirose, 2008, p.88). In other words, human anatomy is mechanically flawed; the use of forelimbs as manipulators necessitates a bipedal configuration, resulting in mechanically unsound, long-term stress on the skeletal system and associated structural failures. However, technology presents a solution. In an attempt to help a paraplegic student, UC Berkeley Professor H. Kazerooni and his class are currently developing “an exoskeleton that [gives the wearer]… the ability to walk” (Vlahos, 2011, p. 57). This exoskeleton, optimized for low weight and moderate price, is designed as an augment to the human body, allowing those with damaged skeletal or neural anatomies to walk. In addition to its tremendous help to the paraplegic, however, Kazerooni’s invention has greater implications for humanity as a whole. That modern technology can enhance damaged bodies to allow near-normal functionality suggests the possibility of further enhancement: the full development of exoskeleton technology that augments the physical capacities of the human body, and mitigates its flaws. In fact, this physical enhancement exoskeleton is currently under development. HULC, or the Human Universal Load Carrier, is a Lockheed Martin research project described as “a completely un-tethered, hydraulic-powered anthropomorphic exoskeleton” (HULC, 2011). The device, which allows the user to lift up to 200 pounds and trek long distances across various terrains with minimal physical exertion, affords true superhuman strength to the wearer. HULC is currently an exclusively military project. It is foreseeable, however, that in fifty years, such exoskeleton enhancement technologies would be as affordable as today’s car. As exoskeletons become more affordable, commonplace, and even necessary in day-to-day living, humanity may become truly integrated with its machines.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;While integrated with mechanical devices, however, humanity is still limited by the frailty of its own physiology: soft, fragile organs that can be damaged, destroyed, or worn out from long-term operation. In fifty years, though, humanity may see the rise of affordable, advanced artificial replacement organs, known by many as the holy grail of biotechnology. This technology is already under development; just recently, a Swedish man had his cancerous trachea replaced “by the world's first artificial trachea, made of his own stem cells grown on a man-made plastic matrix” (Sternberg, 2011, p.06a). This trachea, a comparatively simple organ, was constructed in a highly complex process that involved dripping the patient’s adult stem cells onto the aforementioned plastic matrix, and turning the artificial organ on a rotisserie-like machine, resulting in an organ made entirely out of the patient’s own cells, eliminating any chance of rejection. This technology, now a tried and true option for replacement of certain simple damaged organs, is a viable option for extending life, and diminishing some of the limitations of our human anatomy. There remains a major problem, though; without replacements for more complex organs, humanity may not yet have the ability to transcend the aging of its corporal components. Fortunately, research in the fabrication of more complex artificial organs is making remarkable progress. According to Astrophysicist Neil DeGrasse Tyson, tissue engineering experts have been experimenting with cadaver organ protein frameworks—dead organs with their cells destroyed—dripping new cells onto them (Apsell, 2011). These cells would grow into the frameworks, forming fully functional, complex organs like hearts and lungs. Tyson predicts that within years, there will be “human organs built on natural or artificial scaffolds … made from the patient’s own cells to avoid rejection… in an unlimited supply” (Apsell, 2011). As a result, in fifty years, humanity will see affordable replacement organs of every variety. This has implications beyond extended lifespans and the transcendence of the operational limitations of human organs; replacement organs can help enhance the body, thereby maintaining youthful health, or even youthful efficiency. Biotechnology and tissue engineering will, in essence, not only sustain, but increase the operational efficiency of the human body. In doing so, humanity will transcend the limits of the human body.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Despite leaps and bounds in mechanical and biological enhancements to the human strength and health, the transition from human to trans-human cyborg would be incomplete without enhancements to the mind that allow the brain to interface directly with technology. These technological developments may seem far off, but according to inventor R. Kurzweil, within the next fifty years, “we will merge with the intelligent technology that we are creating. We are already placing intelligent devices in our bodies and brains” (2008, pp. 37-38). Kurzweil refers to modern medical practices like the placement of microchips or small computers into the brains of Parkinson’s disease patients, which interface directly with the electrochemical media of the brain. Neurobiological computational systems such as these might eventually allow humanity to directly interface with its technology, completing the marriage between human and machine. Neurologist R. Restak reaffirms this conclusion, predicting the development of a “‘Neuron transistor’—a fusion of the ‘wet’ form of biological information processing using living tissues with digital electronics” (2008, p.76) within the next fifty years. As stated by Restak, the neuron transistor, an advanced neurobiological-computational interface, would allow a more advanced interface with electronics, permitting an even greater degree of neurological enhancement and brain-machine communication. This advanced technology would allow for developments like those predicted by United States coordinator of Security Richard Clarke, in which “it is entirely possible that we will be able to have our biological brains … interacting directly with silicon-based computer memory chips and related devices. This raises the prospect of adding memory to human brains” (2008, 70). If the neuron transistor is perfected within the next fifty years, a likely advancement from modern neurobiological-computational interfaces, it logically follows that, as Clarke states, the human brain will undergo enhancements in both its memory and processing power. Such technological advancements would likely allow the human race to transcend even the most fundamental limits of our anatomy: the limitations of human intelligence and the lifespan of the brain. Thus, through advancements in neurobiological-computational interface technology, humanity will further enhance its mental capacities.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;After enhancing the human mind, augmenting intelligence, and connecting the brain to directly interface with machinery, there remains anatomical limitation for humanity to transcend: the limitation of the senses. By 2050, however, augmented reality technologies are likely to enhance and revolutionize the human senses, thereby enhancing humanity’s perception of the world. Augmented reality is defined simply as a technology that “adds something to, improves, or heightens, reality” (MacKay, 2011). This includes the projection of comments, games, three-dimensional art, or even advertisements onto empty or blank space in the real world (MacKay, 2011). Currently, augmented reality technologies are limited to devices that would be considered primitive in the technologically integrated world fifty years from now, such as the iPhone 5 or Android smart phones. The cameras on these devices, combined with internet access, allow the device to display merged data from both the real and virtual worlds—an augmented reality. Nevertheless, these media of data transmission to the human mind would be considered primitive in a world in which the human has largely merged with its technology. A different technology postulated by Richard Clark may remedy the situation. According to Clark, people can now buy “hearing aids that are also linked to their mobile telephones, so that what allows them to hear things happening nearby will also connect them to internet packets carrying voice through cyberspace” (2008, p.70). Clark later predicts developments in this technology, allowing an internet interface in all five of the principal human senses. This has tremendous implications for augmented reality technologies; the integrated real world and virtual data of this technology can now be displayed directly into the human senses, thereby enhancing the human body’s ability to perceive the world. With the ability to augment our senses by integrating them with the virtual world, or perhaps with sensors that detect properties of the environment that are imperceptible to the unaided senses, the human race would finally transcend the anatomical limitations of their senses.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The human race as we know it will have, in fifty years, integrated itself with its technology, as man and machine become one. Exoskeleton technology will mollify the mechanical flaws of the human body, and organ replacements will mitigate the perishability of human biology. Neurobiological Computational interfaces will link the human mind to its technologies, and sensory enhancements will allow enhanced perception of the environment. It logically follows, with all these developments, that the human race will have become fully integrated with its machines; by enhancing itself with technology, the human body will have reached a new stage of its evolution. We will become the biological-mechanical medleys of science fiction; the cyborg dawn is near.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Reference List&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Apsell, P. (Producer). (2011). Can we live forever? [Nova sciencenow]. Arlington, VA: PBS.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Clarke, R. (2008). What does it mean to be human?. In M. Wallace (Ed.) The way we will be&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;50 years from today: 60 of the world’s greatest minds share their views of the next half&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;century. (pp. 68-73). Nashville, TN: Thomas Nelson.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Hirose, S. (2008). Where are all the robots?. In M. Wallace (Ed.) The way we will be 50&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;years from today: 60 of the world’s greatest minds share their views of the next half&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;century. (pp. 86-89). Nashville, TN: Thomas Nelson.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;HULC (2011). HULC. Retrieved from http://www.lockheedmartin.com/products/hulc/&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Kurzweil, R. (2008). Porgress accelerates exponentially. In M. Wallace (Ed.) The way&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;we will be 50 years from today: 60 of the world’s greatest minds share their views&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;of the next half century. (pp. 33-38). Nashville, TN: Thomas Nelson.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Mackay, C. (September 20, 2011). Augmented reality: 5 ways it can change your world.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Retrieved from http://www.socialmediaexaminer.com/augmented-reality-5-ways-it-can&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;-change-your-world/&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Restak, R. (2008). A brain scientist’s perspective. In M. Wallace (Ed.) The way we will&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;be 50 years from today: 60 of the world’s greatest minds share their views of the next&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;half century. (pp. 74-77). Nashville, TN: Thomas Nelson.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Sternberg, S. (8 July 2011). Patient gets world’s first artificial trachea. USA Today, p. 06a&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Vlahos, J. (September 2011). First Steps of a Cyborg. Popular Science, 279(3), pp.56-89.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Zewail, A. (2008). The world in fifty years: revolutions and repercussions. In M. Wallace (Ed.)&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The way we will be 50 years from today: 60 of the world’s greatest minds share their&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;views of the next half century. (pp. 228-232). Nashville, TN: Thomas Nelson.
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>Quantum Computing: The Next Paradigm shift in Computing Technology</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2011-12</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The entire history of the computer has been comprised of a series of paradigm shifts. The first computer, the abacus, represented information using a series of primitive ten-state bead matrices. Using this primitive computer, it was possible to do simple arithmetic, albeit at a relatively slow speed. Then Pascaline, the first mechanical computer that used a medley of n-state gears that represented information in a slightly more efficient way, allowed faster calculations. Then, the most dramatic paradigm shift to date, binary information representation, arrived in the form of the vacuum tube, and then the transistor. However, is the transistor the final frontier? What happens when we reach the limit of Moore’s Law, the idea that human computer technology can be miniaturized, and increase exponentially in computing power? New breakthroughs in science may be the answer. Developments in the field of quantum mechanics have demonstrated the possibility of using the uncertain properties of atoms to create quantum computers. According to physicists E Rieffel and W Polak, the advent of quantum computing technology “may radically change the way we have to think about computation, programming, and complexity.” [1] Quantum computing will bring the advent of exponential growth in humanity’s computing power. It will revolutionize the sciences, cryptography, and computing. Although quantum computing technology is still in development and has several technical hurdles to surmount, scientists are rapidly producing solutions to these problems, and humanity may soon see the dawn of the quantum transistor. Thus, quantum computing technology will soon change computing technology as we know it.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;First and foremost, how does a quantum computer work, and what makes it any different from a classical computer? As the name suggests, the quantum computer uses the principles of quantum mechanics to do operations. The fundamental principle of quantum mechanics, the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle, states that “the position and momentum of a particle cannot both be accurately known at the same time.”[2] Because the act of measuring either a particle’s position or momentum changes the other, for particles with infinitesimal mass, there can be a large amount of uncertainty; this implies that the positions and momenta of all particles have some degree of uncertainty, and that the universe and its fundamental laws are ultimately probabilistic. Taken one logical step further, quantum mechanics implies that every particle has an infinite number of potential paths it can take, and, more importantly, manifests all of them until the particle is observed or measured. Quantum computing takes advantage of this highly uncertain state of particles on the atomic scale. The quantum analog of the transistor, the qubit, has an extended flexibility and versatility, making it far superior to its classical counterparts. According to a recent journal on quantum computing, “[i]n addition to the “classical” states (0) and (1), a qubit can be in any superposition (0 and 1).”[3] The difference between the quantum and classical computer, thus, lies in its representation of information; while the classical computer only allows the representation of one 1 or 0 for each transistor, the quantum computer, can represent both a 1 and a 0 at the same time, as well as all values in between. Using the uncertainty principle’s effect on atomic properties like spin, the quantum computer can represent a 1 or a 0, but because both conditions manifest in the absence of observation, the atom can hold a 1, a 0, or both a 1 and a 0. This factor is the distinction between the classical and quantum computer makes the quantum computer the next logical paradigm shift in the evolution of the computer, as it revolutionizes the volume of information that can be represented. Thus, the quantum computer’s distinction comes from its use of quantum, instead of classical mechanics to store and process data.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;But why go through all the technical trouble to build a quantum computer? Quantum computers will help human computing technology to grow by unimaginable leaps and bounds, far beyond the predicted rate of Moore’s Law. First and foremost, Quantum Computing will accelerate processor miniaturization and power. A basic principle of classical computing is that computing power is directly proportional to the number of transistors. This means that the size of the processor and its power must be directly proportional; to achieve an exponentially powerful computer, it is necessary to increase its size, and therefore, cost, exponentially. However, the processing power of a quantum computer increases exponentially with the number of qubits.[3][1] This implies a principle known as Quantum Parallelism, defined by Quantum Computing pioneers D Deutsch and R Jonza as the fact that “an exponential increase in parallelism requires only a linear increase in the amount of physical space needed.”[1] Consequently, Quantum Computing will allow computers and processors to be further miniaturized, past the atomic limit of Moore’s law. Since processing power rises exponentially with qubit density, it will be possible to forge computers of incredible power with only a small set of atoms. This quantum leap in miniaturization will allow further progress in other technologies, like nanorobotics or portable processing. Furthermore, Quantum Computing will greatly enhance humanity’s processing capabilities. According to MIT researchers, “[d]ue to the fact that qubits can represent both a 1 and a 0, however, each qubit can process more than one operation at a time.”[4] In other words, because of the qubit’s exploitation of the uncertainty principle, and its ability to simultaneously manifest a 1 and a 0 in the absence of an observer, the quantum computer will be drastically more powerful than the classical computer. This ability of qubits to do many calculations at once will bring the advent of new standards of computational speeds. Super fast quantum computers will revolutionize modern cryptography as computations that previously would take centuries become problems that can be solved in seconds. At the same time, the advent of quantum computing technology will bring new cryptographic algorithms previously impractical due to slow computing speeds. Furthermore, the increased computing speeds of quantum computing can accelerate the march of science in quantum mechanics itself. According to physicist Richard Feynman, “certain quantum mechanical effects cannot be simulated efficiently on a classical computer.”[1] Classical computers simply cannot do these quantum calculations in a reasonable amount of time. Quantum computers, however, run on the very principles that govern the quantum scale, and will allow the efficient processing of quantum simulations. Thus, quantum computers provide immeasurable advantages over classical computers, and will revolutionize computer science.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Despite its promise, quantum computing technology is still riddled with technical hurdles. Nevertheless, scientists are on the brink of a breakthrough that will solve most of these problems. One of the largest problems with quantum computing lies in the fundamental nature of the uncertainty principle; a particle on a quantum scale loses its quantum properties, that is to say, its ability to simultaneous manifest multiple states, when measured or observed. As stated by Rieffel and Polak, “Accessing the results is equivalent to making a measurement, which disturbs the quantum state.”[1] This is problematic, because any computer needs to measure the states of its transistors in order to function. Measuring a qubit directly, however, will force it to revert to either a 1 or a 0 randomly, turning it into a mere classical transistor. Modern quantum mechanics, however, has a solution. A peculiar phenomenon in the quantum world, known as quantum entanglement, allows the indirect observation of qubits, which, in turn, allows the measurement of the qubit’s properties without disrupting its simultaneous states. Simply put, Quantum Entanglement is “a curious property of quantum physics that links the condition and behavior of two or more particles, such as atoms or photons.”[5] The properties of entangled particles are the same, and changes to the properties of one particle will instantly effect changes in those of the other. Thus, one need not observe qubits directly to measure them; it is only necessary to observe a particle entangled with the qubit. Through the use of entanglement, it will be possible to make a simple, practical, and most importantly, scalable quantum computer. Though modern quantum computers are rather limited, with the most sophisticated ones having 2 qubits and the processing equivalent of a four-function calculator that can only count to four, with the observation dilemma fixed, quantum computing technology will likely develop rapidly in the next decade.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Quantum computing will soon revolutionize the modern world. Using the principles of quantum mechanics and the uncertainty principle, quantum computers can do what classical computers cannot. Quantum computers will allow growth by leaps and bounds in miniaturization and computing speed. The technical hurdles that impede the process of said technology will soon be uprooted by new science. Thus, the advent of quantum computing is near. Modern science and technology will soon take the quantum leap.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cited References&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[1] Rieffel E, Polak W. An introduction to quantum computing for non-physicists. ACM Computing Surveys. 2000;32( 3):300-302.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[2] Krauskopf KB, Beiser A. The physical universe. McGraw Hill (NY):2003. 276.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[3] Technion Computer Science Department. Quantum computing without entanglement. Report. Hafia, Israel: Technion: 2003. 1-4.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[4] Massachusetts Institute of Technology.  MIT researchers create quantum computer that simulates quantum system. MIT News [Internet]. Cambridge (MA): Massachusetts Institute of Technology; c1999. 1999 [cited 2011, Dec 4]; Avaliable from http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/1999/quantum.html&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[5]NBCUniversal. Quantum computing gets boost from entanglement Of atom pairs. Science Daily [Internet]. c2006. 2006 [cited 2011, Dec 4]; Avaliable from: http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2006/10/061018150842.htm
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>Student Self-Perception</title>
		<grade>ESHS 2011-12</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The topic of student self-perception, and its effect on student career choices and academic patterns, has been long studied by educational scholars and professionals. The scope of previous work is broad, covering issues from whether or not student self perception has a measurable and statistically significant effect on performance and career choices, to the factors that influence student self-perception. First of all, studies on student self-perception show a strong, clear, and positive correlation between self-perception and academic performance, and provide data that imply causation. Furthermore, they address the influence of factors like gender, appearance, or classroom conditions can have on academic self-perception. Lastly, some of these studies address teaching methodology and other changes that can be made to increase student self-perception and develop the resource of student psychology. Through these studies, we have found that student self-perception has a strong impact on academic performance, is controlled by a complex cocktail of interacting psychological and psychical factors, and can be improved by various changes in classroom methodology.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;First of all, previous studies on this topic have established the importance of student self-perception on academic performance. In a study by R. Stringer and N. Heath, students in a traditional classroom setting took a survey designed to assess each student’s academic self-perception, and a baseline exam to measure base academic performance. Each student then received a second exam at the end of the academic year. The findings of the study indicated that “[t]he children's self-perceptions of academic competence accounted for significant variance in academic performance one year later” (2008 p. 327). The fact that the variance in student performance could be explained by self-perception suggests that there is a relationship between self-perception and academic ability. This experiment was reasonably controlled, and, as measures were taken to limit confounding variables and other such experimental artifacts, it appears that self-perception and academic performance are clearly linked. Although it should be noted that this study also states that academic self-perception cannot be used as a flawless predictor of the magnitude of academic success (Stringer 2008 p. 327), the positive association between academic performance and self-perception are rather clear. Another study, conducted by K. Rudasill et al., similarly suggests the importance of student self-perception. In the observational study, the researchers surveyed gifted students, and took note of their degree of academic success. The survey, which takes into account data from gifted adolescent students, suggests that within the population of gifted students, “[a] positive self-concept may lead to higher educational and career aspirations, whereas a poorer self-concept may negatively influence choices and outcomes” (2009 p. 300). The importance of student self-perception with respect to career pathways and academic performance, thus, is relatively clear.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Now that we have established the importance of the issue of student self-perception, it is now necessary to look into previous research with regards to the factors that determine student self-perception. One of the most prevalent of these factors is gender.  A study by K. Rudasill and C. Callahan, which surveyed boys and girls from grades 9 through 12, suggests that “(a) girls' self-perceptions of ability scores were higher than boys' in humanities, and boys planned to take more math courses than girls; (b) academically advanced students' self-perceptions of ability correlated with their future coursework plans” (300, 2010), and that these differences bear a significant correlation with self-perception, owed to the effects of gender stereotypes. It is notable that when asked about their future coursework loads and plans,  boys were significantly more likely to indicate a technical courseload, while girls tended more strongly towards the humanities (Rudasill 2010 p. 313). This indicates that self-perception, a likely motivator behind this disparity, is associated with the performance gap between the two genders in math and humanities. It logically follows that gender strongly influences student self-perception. Classroom environments can also have a significant effect on self-perception. According to another study on elementary school teaching methodology, “students … appeared to adopt approach goals more than avoidance goals” (Sungur 2010 p. 303). This study divides classroom tactics into two categories; the method of approach goals rewards students for proper behavior or correct answers, while avoidance goals punish students for improper answers or behavior. Sungur then goes on to suggest that the difference between these methodologies can mean a marked difference in student self-perception. As such, factors like gender differences, or even a different classroom environment, can influence student self-perception and its associated effects on academic aptitude.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Understanding the factors that determine student self-perception empowers educators and school administrators to make policy and methodology changes that would help improve student self-perception, and tap into this valuable psychological resource. In a journal by D. Miller and F. Lavin, educational innovators have discovered a technique that integrates the aforementioned factors to improve student self-perception. This technique, known as formative assessment, involves qualitative, as opposed to quantitative feedback, in which teachers give personal and personalized feedback to students.  Miller and Lavin’s results are promising, as “Gains were seen in self-esteem and in beliefs about competence” (2007 p. 3) by the end of the study.  Furthermore, Miller and Lavin found that students undergoing the formative assessment methodology improved dramatically in their academic performance. Through protocols like formative assessment, thus, it is possible to improve student self-perception.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Student self-perception is an important factor in determining academic performance. Factors like gender and classroom environment can influence this critical factor, and through new didactic processes like formative assessment, it is possible to develop teaching methodologies that efficiently and easily improve self-perception. It is clear that educators should take measures to improve student self-perception, and unlock the potential of academic psychology. Past studies suggests that it is productive and feasible to do so. El Segundo High School should refocus its efforts in developing teaching methodologies that both reinforce key concepts, and improve student confidence and academic self-perception.
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>Environmental Legacy: A Product of Class Struggle</title>
		<grade>Berkeley Fall 2012</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Earth is our life-support system, the proverbial birthplace of civilization. Society, however, has left its mark on its nurturer; humanity’s actions have altered the ground state of the natural order, leaving long-term effects that change the social and biological fabric of communities. Human intervention in biosphere has left an environmental legacy in its wake. This legacy has consequences that include social deterioration and health problems. Ideally, the problems associated with our environmental meddling should affect all equally. However the costs and benefits of humanity’s environmental legacy have a noticeable pattern of distribution, one of social injustice. Dr. Robert D. Bullard, Dean and Professor of Sociology of Texas Southern University, documents this injustice as he discusses various cases of environmental racism and classism in his work, Dumping in Dixie: Race, Class, and Environmental Quality. Specifically, Bullard argues that the benefits derived from polluting activities feed the upper and middle classes’ luxurious standard of living, while the poor and powerless bear the consequences. This suggests a probable cause of humanity’s destructive environmental legacy and its inequitable distribution: class struggle. Thus, environmental legacy consists of the short and long term effects of human actions in the natural and social orders of a locality. The distribution and perpetuation of the ecological and human costs of our environmental legacy is a product of class struggle.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The Consequences of our Environmental Legacy&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Environmental legacy consists of any human interaction with nature and the aggregate sum of its short and long-term effects. Ecological activist and Green Party nominee Winona La Duke gives a specific instance of this in her study on the effects of uranium mining on local Native American populations, titled Red Land and Uranium Mining: How the Search for Energy is Endangering Indian Tribal Lands. In it, she states that the effects of uranium mining on these populations are difficult to diagnose and repair because not only is radiation undetectable, but “also the effects often take almost 20 years to appear in the general population” (La Duke, 1981, p.65). According to La Duke, the aftermath of uranium mining is seen in the radioactivity that lingers in reservations long after the mines have closed. It is clear that the environmental legacy of radioisotope mining lies in its long term physiological and ecological effects. However, La Duke also points out the short term effects of uranium mining, including irradiation of the local populace and radioactive contamination of local food and water resources. Long before health effects began to appear in the Native American mining families, the groundwater and rivers near the Rio Pagute have undergone “heavy contamination with radiation” (La Duke, 1981, p64). Evidently, environmental legacy also includes the immediate effects of human intervention, as well as those that linger in the surrounding area long after the fact.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Investigating the nature of environmental legacy raises another inquiry: How does environmental legacy shape surrounding communities? Environmental legacy can fundamentally shift the biological, cultural, and social identities of affected peoples; its effects produce tensions between the often disadvantaged victims and the wealthy consumer class. For instance, Rachael Cason, founder of the modern Environmental Movement, underscores the damaging biological effects of parathion pesticides on fieldworkers. In her book, Silent Spring, Carson reports a case in which “eleven out of thirty men picking oranges [treated with Parathion] became violently ill and all but one had to be hospitalized” (Carson, 1962, p.30). Carson, states the health effects of certain pesticides, but more importantly implies that the environmental legacy of pesticide use can result in human costs. Our environmental legacy has serious physiological consequences that can range from immediate to long-term. Also, it is important to note that the victims in Carson’s case study are fieldworkers. Fieldwork is a profession associated with poverty and these fieldworkers are contracted into hazardous working conditions by wealthy business owners. This suggests that economic status and class conflict play a role in the distribution of environmental health hazards, and that this distribution is a marked source of class conflict. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;But the scope of a negative environmental legacy’s effects is not limited to physical changes. Environmental activist and researcher Margaret Amalia Hiesinger demonstrates that the effects of environmental legacy can also change the identity of a community. Her study, The House that Uranium Built: Perspectives on the Effects of Exposure on Individuals and Community, shows how a Navajo uranium mining community was influenced by its industry. A common joke told in this community shows the true extent to which the community’s identity has shifted: “How do you find your kids at night? Just look for the glow” (Heissinger, 1999, p.76). The fact that radiation poisoning and uranium mining has integrated itself into even the humor of this community illustrates a fundamental change in its structure. Just as radioactive materials have become permanently absorbed into the denizens’ bodies, the state of radioactive contamination has integrated itself into their identities. This often results in fear and self-blame (Hiesinger, 1999, p.78), both abrasive forces that disrupt communities. Moreover, the sociocultural shifts in these communities highlight their underlying resentment against those in power, as seen in reservation residents’ reactions to EPA cleanup efforts, which were perceived merely as efforts to give contaminated areas “the appearance of being normal” (Hiesinger, 1999, p.80). Like the identity of contamination, this resentment has become part of the victim communities’ characters. As such, environmental legacy has the power to hurt a community by reshaping its identity, and produces socioeconomic tensions. Hiesinger also shows how environmental legacies cause cultural shifts. This is particularly visible in the Navajo communities in Hiesinger’s study because these cultures have difficulty coping with the effects of uranium mining. Since the concepts of uranium and radioactivity are foreign to Navajo culture, “no established ceremonies exist to effectively heal victims” (Heissinger, 1999, p.79). The environmental legacy of uranium mining not only disrupts the biological and social aspects of the Navajo community, but additionally has the ability to introduce stressors foreign to their culture. Thus, the human cost of our environmental legacy consists not only of biological damage, but also fundamental shifts in the identity and culture.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Distribution and Class Struggle&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The distribution of the problems associated with our environmental footprints is a product of an economic struggle. An expert in environmental justice activism, Dr. Robert D. Bullard of Texas Southern University states that “locally unwanted land uses” such as landfills and chemical dumps, tend to appear more frequently “in poor, powerless, black communities rather than affluent suburbs… even though the benefits derived from industrial production are directly related to affluence” (Bullard, 1990, p.4). Bullard’s statement suggests that the ecological and social problems associated with our environmental legacy are unjustly targeted; environmental problems specifically cluster around poor and minority populations. This “selective victimization”, which ecology researcher Barbara Rose Johnston depicted as an product of “preexisting social conditions [that] result in the loss of critical resources and a healthy environment” (Johnston, 1994, p. 17), is a phenomenon in which pollution and degradation concentrate near economically or otherwise disadvantaged groups. Thus, the distribution patterns of our environmental legacy are a result of an unconscious class struggle between the privileged and the underprivileged. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;However, this struggle, in which our environmental legacy is passed to the poor, is not a one-sided fight. In his book, Bullard depicts grassroots movements rising up in economically disadvantaged, minority communities like Emille-Sumter County, in which “Local opposition to the waste operation has come mainly from… a black grassroots community group… [and] a mostly white umbrella environmental group” (Bullard, 1994, p.63). The fact that both black and white denizens of Emille-Sumter, a racially polemic neighborhood as is, are able to unite as a coalition to push waste management operations away from their community demonstrates that the poor and disadvantaged have the power to resist the oppression of the consumer classes. Bullard portrays this resistance as a sign of hope. Unfortunately, these efforts, which seek to push waste operations ‘elsewhere’, is  just another manifestation of the NIMBY—not in my backyard—phenomenon. In the end, humanity’s environmental legacy remains unchanged as the consumers and the disadvantaged each fight to push the effects away from them themselves, a perpetuation of economic tensions.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Ultimately, the struggle between the privileged and underprivileged is not a fair fight. The poor still bear the brunt of the problems that accompany our environmental legacy due to industry’s often unfair tactics. For example, Johnston documents the tactics used by the uranium milling industry to control its workers. Specifically, the uranium millworkers “were never warned about the radiation hazards associated with millwork” (Johnston et al., 2008, p.97). Appallingly, the millworkers, whose duties involve working in direct exposure to deadly radiation, were purposely kept uninformed of the dangers of their profession. Ignorance makes the victims of our environmental legacy vulnerable, and unable to protest or otherwise change the situation. Meanwhile, this ignorance puts industry at an advantage, as those affected by their polluting activities are kept uninformed. The distribution of our environmental legacy as product of class struggle is apparent. Similarly, Hiesinger’s study shows that corporations often use money as a deceptive device, to put economic pressures on their already poor and needy victims; the mere act of compensation is a means to circumvent “vital reparative measures while leaving an open door for industry and government to continue their quiet killing” (Heissinger, 1999, p. 86). Likewise, Bullard emphasizes that much of the vulnerability of the lower classes comes from their “pro-jobs stance, a kind of ‘don’t bite the hand that feeds you’ sentiment” (Bullard, 1994, p.28). Both Heissinger and Bullard illustrate a vital truth about the class conflict: corporations have the power to use money and jobs—and other economic pressures—to control the needy, lower classes. The promise of food and employment alone can greatly weaken a grassroots environmental justice movement. Consequently, class struggle and economic vulnerability contribute to the perpetuation of environmental injustice.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Environmental legacy consists of an interference with the environment, and the ensuing social and biological consequences. A root cause of today’s dismal environmental legacy is the class conflict between the consumer class and the underprivileged. While environmental problems are omnipresent in the polluted biosphere, they tend to concentrate in poor and underprivileged neighborhoods. These problems, which range from illness to social and cultural deterioration, are severe and wear away at the integrity of these communities. While grassroots movements in these neighborhoods are fighting back to push undesirable industries elsewhere, economic and psychological manipulation by corporations and the privileged create an uneven playing field. This class struggle ultimately constitutes another manifestation of the NIMBY phenomenon and fails to undo our environmental legacy. As such, the poor and otherwise disadvantaged will continue to suffer from degraded and unhealthy environments and communities. The class struggle will continue, and ultimately, our environmental legacy will stay the same. Without unity, nothing will change. After all, earth is a life support system for all people, regardless of race or class. It is imperative to put aside our class struggles, and build a more sustainable future. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Works Cited &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Bullard, Robert D. (1994) Dumping in Dixie: Race, Class, and Environmental Quality. Boulder, Colo: Westview, 2000.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Carson, Rachel. (1962) Silent Spring. Boston and New York: Mariner Books. Chapters 1-3, 12,14&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cole, Lue and Sheila Foster. (2001) From the Ground up: Environmental Racism and the Rise of the Environmental Justice Movement. New York: New York Universty Press. Chapter 1: A History of the Environmental Justice Movement&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Hiesinger, Margaret Amalia. (1999) “The House  that Uranium Built: Perspectives on the Effects on Exposure on Individuals and Community.” The Energy Reader. pp. 113-131.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Johnston, Barbara Rose. (Ed.) (1994) Who Pay’s the Price? The Sociocultural Context of Environmental Crisis. Island Press. Chapters 1 and 2.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Johnston, Barbara and Susan Dawson, Gary Madsen. (2008) “Uranium Mining and Milling: Navajo Experiences in the American Southwest.” The Energy Reader. pp. 132-146&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;La Duke, Winona. (1981) “Red Land and Uranium Mining: How the Search for Energy is Endangering Indian Tribal Lands.” The Energy Reader. pp 105-109
		</text>
	</essay>
	<essay>
		<title>Energy Consumption in the United States: A Recipe for Disaster</title>
		<grade>Berkeley Fall 2012</grade>
		<text>
			&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Modern society is driven by technology. According to PennEnergy, a renewable energy research and development group, America annually consumes 1.0×1011 gigajoules of energy to sustain its industrial and civilian sectors (Moore 2010). This energy goes to power everything from medical equipment to automobiles to the stock market. But while this technological advancement has greatly increased the standard of living in the United States, it is not without its costs. Indeed, recent trends suggest that the American populace’s choices in energy resources have allowed disasters to escalate. In a journal article, Anthropological Research on Hazards and Disasters, anthropologist Anthony Oliver-Smith defines disaster as “the interface of society, technology, and environment” and the aggregate “interactions of these features” (Oliver-Smith p.117, 1996). However, according to anthropology writer and disaster researcher Susanna Hoffman, all disasters are “caused by humans at one level or another” (Hoffman p. 112, 2010). This idea, that there is no such thing as a natural disaster, is not new. The scientific community recognizes that anthropogenic changes to geophysical systems increase the frequency and intensity of nature’s wrath, as seen in disasters like Hurricane Katrina, a 2005 tropical storm that devastated New Orleans. Likewise, historians recognize that a society’s choice in energy source can result in nuclear disasters like Chernobyl, the Three Mile Island partial meltdown, or perhaps more recently, the Fukushima disaster. However, limited supply and increasing demand for energy, especially in the form of foreign oil, has engendered yet another kind of disaster: international conflict. The United States’ demand for energy has allowed imperialistic corporate interests to interfere with foreign powers, producing tensions, conflict, and ultimately war. Energy overconsumption and foreign oil dependence in the United States is a principal contributor to both natural and diplomatic disasters.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;International Conflict and Domestic Turmoil&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Domestic energy consumption contributes directly to corporate imperialism and failures in international relations. Particularly, our dependence on foreign oil promotes a set of imperialistic corporate practices that encourage the development of foreign conflict. According to Columbia University Professor of Modern Arab Studies Rashid Khalidi, as American oil companies tried to wrest additional control over Iraqi oil resources, local populations grew restless. As these American oil interests expanded their occupation regime in the 1970s, “fear of foreign control, born of decades of bitter experience of being forced to watch others dictate the disposition of their countries’ most valuable resource, spread throughout the country and the region” (Khalidi p. 163, 2006). It is notable that the activities of oil interests in the Middle East not only work to exploit foreign resources for domestic profit, but also induce fear of control in the local populace. This suggests that these corporate activities are not simple capitalist exploits, but are rather imperialistic in nature. In fact, Khalidi’s statement illustrates that America’s foreign oil dependence, the primary impetus for these imperialistic enterprises, allows the aggregation of international tensions. And while these tensions do not, in themselves, constitute disaster, they have the potential to develop into full-blown catastrophe. To illustrate, consider the impact of American relations with the Middle East on domestic activities. After decades of foreign occupation and control over natural resources, a group of petroleum producing countries formed OPEC—the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries—and placed an embargo on the western world in 1973. According to Khalidi, the repercussions were immediate and severe. Oil prices “shot up, producing … massive increases in prices for consumers” (Khalidi p.161, 2006). Intolerable gas lines ensued, followed by gasoline rationing. The depth of social and economic disruption caused by the OPEC Embargo qualifies this event as a disaster. The notion that tensions in the Middle East—previously illustrated to be a product of our foreign oil dependence—can result in economic chaos illustrates that American energy consumption patterns can contribute to domestic disaster. Furthermore, it is notable that the OPEC embargo affected all walks of American society, ranging from industrial energy needs to personal uses like transportation. The fact that a change in the supply of a single energy source, oil, can have such a large impact on American society reveals the extent of the vulnerability caused by our energy overconsumption. The magnitude of American energy consumption and our dependence on a small subset of energy resources greatly increases the severity and impact of diplomatic calamities like the OPEC embargo. Thus, America’s energy choices act as a contributor to foreign tensions and domestic disasters.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;The scope of the problems caused by our energy dependence is not limited to economic disasters. Developing international tensions allow conflict to erupt into war. In 1979, after the people of Iran overthrew Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi—an autocrat whom the United States supported— American oil companies saw their overseas pipelines threatened. Almost immediately, the United States government sprang into action to protect what it saw as important American interests. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs William R. Crawford said in an interview that he does “regard the integrity and maintenance of the integrity of the kingdom of Saudi Arabia as vital to American interests in the Middle East, and would—should be prepared to act in implementation of that consideration” (Commoner p. 153, 1979). Crawford would later agree that this rather roundabout account amounts to a statement of intentions to go to war to protect American access to Saudi Oil (Commoner 153, 1979). As previously established, however, the international tensions that would threaten these oil companies’ petroleum supplies arise from the imperialistic nature of foreign oil exploitation. The very circumstance that we, as a nation, depend on foreign oil for a considerable portion of the energy consumed in the domestic market is a root cause of war and other entanglements of the United States in the Middle East. Therefore, domestic energy consumption can cause the disaster of war.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;‘Natural’ Disasters&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Our energy consumption has contributed to geophysical changes that threaten our livelihoods. Modern meteorology and climatology have established a link between oil dependence, global warming, and the severity of supposedly natural disasters. As stated by Environmental Studies research fellow Roger Pielke, “[a]nthropogenic climate change has the potential for … increasing the intensity of tropical cyclones through warming of sea surface temperatures” (Pielke p. E11, 2005). Pielke’s mention of anthropogenic climate change refers to changes to climate patterns, namely global warming, due to human activities rather than geologic cycles. Since anthropogenic global warming is known to be a direct result of oil and coal consumption, it is reasonable to conclude that America’s fossil fuel dependence is directly and causally related to the frequency and severity of tropical storms. This reaffirms that there are no natural disasters, and all calamities are in some part a result of human activities. In this case, the escalating severity of seasonal weather extremities is a product of our energy overconsumption and dependence on fossil fuels. A specific instance of a disaster exacerbated by anthropogenic climate change would be Hurricane Katrina, a storm widely publicized as the first of its kind to cause such extensive damage. Dave Eggers’ 2010 novel, Zeitoun, documents the tragic circumstances faced by Abdulrahman Zeitoun, a common denizen of New Orleans during this storm. Eggers describes the fallout of the storm only hours after the initial rains have stopped: “the levees had been overtopped or compromised. There could be no doubt. The city would soon be underwater” (Eggers p. 85 2010). The mere fact that Katrina had enough energy to overtop and breach the New Orleans levees, a set of flooding safeguards designed to protect the city from storms like these, illustrates its severity. The intensity of hurricane Katrina and that of similar, recent storms like 2012’s Hurricane Sandy illustrate that energy overconsumption and overdependence on hydrocarbon energy resources can have tragic consequences. Particularly, the geophysical changes wrought by our energy choices have increased the intensity of supposedly natural storms. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;In addition to worsening climactic disasters, our energy consumption has forced us to turn to unsafe energy alternatives, creating the potential for manmade physical disasters. With increasing oil prices in post-1970 America, energy companies have been increasingly forced to turn to other concentrated power sources like nuclear. History, however, has shown the consequences of this shift. Three Mile Island, a nuclear reactor in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, underwent a partial meltdown in 1979. And though government agencies and the media claim that only a small amount of radioactive materials escaped the reactor, alternative energy activist Harvey Wasserrman states that “nobody knows how much radiation escaped from Three Mile Island. Nobody knows where it went. And nobody knows what the impact was” (“Three Mile Island” p. 168, 2009). The notion that any measurable amount of radiation escaped the reactor suggests that the Three Mile Island accident and nuclear energy in general have dire consequences. After all, “radiation affects people irrespective of dosage” (Hiesinger p.85, 1999). But with dwindling energy supplies in the 1970s and no economical means to quickly implement clean, renewable energy, where else does the United States have to turn in the face of oil embargoes, price hikes, and global warming? The sheer demand for energy has forced American energy suppliers to turn to alternatives like nuclear that have the potential to cause disaster. Hence, our dependence on nuclear energy is ultimately a result of our energy overconsumption. With this dependence comes the potential for disaster.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;In closing, America’s energy consumption and dependence on foreign resources to satisfy domestic energy demands is a root cause of the escalation of natural and diplomatic disasters. Our foreign oil dependence creates corporate imperialism and international tensions, especially in the Middle East. These tensions erupt into economic disasters like the OPEC embargo, but also have the potential to produce a full-blown war. Meanwhile, our dependence on fossil fuels has caused critical changes to geophysical processes, increasing the intensity of seasonal storms and other supposedly natural disasters. Furthermore, to satisfy the insatiable domestic energy market, energy suppliers have turned to dangerous energy sources like nuclear power that, as demonstrated by the Three Mile Island incident, have the potential to erupt into calamity. The link between disaster and energy consumption illustrates that catastrophe is a result of human activities. And if we fail to work towards sustainability and energy independence, disasters and diplomatic conflict will continue to escalate. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Works Cited&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Commoner, Barry. “Prologue,” The Politics of Energy. In Laura Nader’s The Energy Reader. Pp. 198-204.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Eggers, Dave. (2009) Zeitoun. San Francisco: McSweeny’s Books.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Hiesinger, Margaret Amalia. (1999) “The House that Uranium Built: Perspectives on the Effects of Exposure on Individuals and Community.” In Laura Nader’s The Energy Reader. Pp. 113-131&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Hoffman, Susanna M. (2010) “Of Increasing Concern: Disaster and the Field of Anthropology” Anthropology News 51(7):3-4&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Khalidi, Rashid. “The Middle East: Geostrategy and Oil.” In Laura Nader’s The Energy Reader. Pp. 271-281.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Moore, J. R. "US Energy Consumption: How Much Do We Use?" - Pennenergy. N.p., n.d. Web. 31 Oct. 2012. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Oliver-Smith, A. (1996) “Anthropological Research on Hazards and Disasters.” Annual Review of Anthropology 25: 303-328.&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Pielke, R. A., C. Landsea, M. Mayfield, J. Laver, and R. Pasch. "Hurricanes and Global Warming." Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society 86.11 (2005): 1571-575. Print.
		</text>
	</essay>
</essaylist>

